hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and this is Shan and in today's topic uh
I will cover all the annotations which
are covered in uh yellow the green this
spring boot application I have already
covered in the first part introduction
to Spring boot uh where I will
explaining about the difference between
spring mvy and spring boot right you
remember so let's focus on this yellow
annotations today so let's start without
wasting any time so I think you can read
call this diagram from the first
introduction to Spring boot where the
dispatcher ofet whenever any user hit
any API let's say fetch user get call so
what dispatcher sofl will do it will
make use of Handler mapping to identify
the controller which can handle this
request okay so what all the annotations
which generally you can say that uh
helps uh doing this handling mapping
Handler mapping right so we will see
those so as part of this all the
annotations which I'm am going to tell I
will tell you why it is required what
the purpose it solved but how exactly
these annotations created how exactly
spring boot or Java understand read this
uh annotations those are beyond the
scope of today's topic so that you will
understand more about in the Java like
I've already mentioned Java is the
prerequisite right right so in the Java
playlist Basics to advance uh check out
the 18 number video annotations I have
covered in depth you will get more
better
understanding okay so let's start that
in the Handler mapping if you see that
the first and foremost is this
annotation at theate
controller right on the second is like
you can also have at theate rest
controller they are same they solve the
same purpose with a minor very minor
difference so what atate controller and
atate rest controllers tell to the
spring so it indicate that this class is
responsible for handling incoming HTTP
request so there can be let's say 100 of
controller classes so spring boot will
include this
also right then determine whether this
particular controller class can be used
for to handle any specific API which
user has invoked or not that is again it
has to determine that we will see but at
least this controller will this
classes which has this
annotations actually get it into the
list of the controller classes because
the only these
classes spring boot will consider that
yes you guys are eligible to handle the
HTTP
request okay
so what is the difference between at
theate controller and atate rest
controller so there is a very minor
difference that at theate rest
controller is your controller plus
response body annotation here if you see
in the controller class every
method I have used at theate response
body but in the rest controller here if
you see in every method I haven't used
at theate response body so what does at
theate response body annotations mean so
atate response body tells that the
return type of the
method the return type of the method
should be considered as your HTTP
response right so if you don't write
this let's say what would happen if you
don't write at theate response body
what a spring boot will
do whatever the return type so return
type is a string so let's say I am
instead of returning this big I am
returning let's say just
hello I am returning just hello so what
springboard will do springbot will try
to uh resolve this so it will considered
as the name of a view and it will try to
resolve this let's say hello so it will
try to say that hey hello.js p is there
any view like this it will try to look
for it and then if it find it it will
try to render it on the
UI okay but with the response body we
are specifically telling to the
springboard that hey this is not a view
which you have to render this is a HTTP
response body right sand it it sand as
it is don't consider as a view consider
it as a rest
response okay but now you can tell hey
for the rest controller why this
response body is not required on this
each method why because here if you see
that in the rest controller rest
controller is nothing but a
controller with response
body right so you don't specifically
have to mention at every method that the
response type should spring boot should
not consider the response type as a view
name consider is as a rest HTTP response
only so that's why generally you can say
that everywhere you will find we are
using rest controller rather than
controller because it's pretty
convenient that you don't have to put
rest response body in each
method okay now here is the second part
here if you see that something called
request map mapping which actually does
the mapping of a
API okay so now we have defined the
controller class now we have defined the
controller class that okay this is the
class I have called it a
controller this is the class I have
called it rest controller
okay so what all apis this controller is
hosting so now I am writing those what
all apis this controller is hosting so
let's say this is one API SL getet
call
fetch
user and another is let's say
post save user let's say these two apis
I want to host into this controller so
how how I can do that using request
mapping so now now let's say this is the
method I have written get user detail
here I have all the business logic to go
search and DB do whatever get the
details of the user and return it but
now I want to map this
API that whenever a user invoke this
API this particular method should get
invoked okay so what I have to do is
first of all the starting point of of
the method the this method should be
hosted in controller you know already
why because dispatcher Ser only
considered controllers only okay so this
method the all the logic right so
generally this method should be present
into controller and now we have to add
the mapping mapping of
what this API to this method we have to
map it so this is annotation called at
the rate request mapping
right as the name says that it is
mapping the request to what to this
method so here if you now go and check
this
annotation at theate request
mapping you will find
certain
methods right so one of the thing is
parameter is like
path what is the path or what is the
your
API path slash fetch user so I have
defined SL fetch user so here I can also
use
value right so here if you see that here
they have told either you can use value
or path and they have given the alas so
value is considered alas for path and
this path is alas for Value so whatever
names suit you better you can use that
to understand so I always find link with
that path is actually which defines this
URL so I mostly use
path the second is like method whether
it's a get request Port uh post request
put request delete request you can use
here so there is something called
method so you can choose like whether
it's a get post put patch delete
whatever it request is you can tell
right now here if you see that this
annotation request mapping annotation it
has this
two annotations also at theate mapping
at theate reflective so this annotations
what generally spring boot denotes to
the spring boot that it has to do the
mapping here the mapping logic so see
all this logic is generally internal to
a spring board and it is resolved
through reflection right it is resolved
through reflection which you will get to
know how uh in this uh annotation so all
the annotations are resolved through
reflection
only so in the request mapping these two
annotations actually helps doing the
mapping so here if you see this at the
rate reflective controller mapping
reflective processor so here what it is
doing controller mapping reflective
processor so if you go internally and
check right what it is doing is it is
doing actually the reflection
and it is ultimately task is to do the
controller mapping as the name
suggest it's do the mapping okay this
controller has all can handle all this
apis let's say get API is handled by
sample controller this API is handled by
also sample controller so all this
mapping is generally happen here in the
reflective part in the second uh
alternative here if you see I have used
this like instead of this
line I have used it like this atate get
mapping now if you see atate get
mapping so at theate get mapping is
nothing but a request
mapping but with a
method request method.
getet so ultimately what it is just
simplifying or adding little bit more
readability that this method equals to
get you don't have to now write it
specifically in the get mapping it is Al
specifically set the default value of
this method is get only you just have to
give the path right since get mapping is
also a request mapping you will have all
the values path value and all would be
present so you can give path that this
is a fetch
user right similarly if you have uh post
request you can do write post mapping so
both are right but generally you can say
that this is mostly preferred like
because of easily
readability and also just to notice one
more thing that this uh request mapping
right you can also write at a class
level now let's say your API is
something like this at theate API
SL fetch user
at theate API
SL save user so now here if you see
these are the
common in all the apis which you are
hosting in this controller then instead
of writing like uh here path equals to/
API SL fetch user SL API slave user what
it will do is at the class level we can
use a mapping and provide a value or
path whichever you feel right and
provide the common part so at theate API
is common right so you can provide at
the top and in the below
one you can just write the remaining
path right so it will ultimately get
appended so whenever uh the mapping will
actually happen so mapping would happen
like at theate API SL fetch
user right this is the get
call it belongs to which controller this
controller sample
controller right and which method it has
to invoke it has to invoke this get user
details method so these mappings will be
done because that logic is still present
in the request mapping
only
okay
so so now you understand this
controller rest controller what's the
difference between them response body
also we
know request mapping I have already uh
Told You So the next we have is
something called request parameter so
here if you see that uh let's see this
API so in this API this is nothing but a
host this is your
path right this is your path like / API
SL fetch user and after this question
mark you will see this is your first
request parameter this is your second
separated by end and this is your third
separated by
end okay so there are three request
parameters so request parameter is
generally started after question mark it
helps to bind the request parameter to
controller method
parameter how so here I have created a
very simple class sample controller I
have annotated with rest controller to
tell the springut that this class
consider this class it might host
certain apis what API now I'm doing the
mapping I have put the rest request
mapping at the rate request mapping to
consider this as a common part so I put
it at the
above now I have created this method
which will host all the logic to get the
user
details now this uh method I have done a
mapping for this API path so I have put
the get request because it's a get call
right so at theate get mapping I have
put the path so it will do a mapping of
this to this
method now this request parameter three
request parameters I have to map it to
this member method member method
variables so how I can map it through
request parameter so here if you see
that I have put atate request
parameter and the name which I have used
is like first name exact naming here for
this request
parameter right and the value of it Shan
will get set under this first
name and there is also one more thing
called required so default value is true
so means let's say that for this first
name I haven't tell required so means
this is mandatory when a user invoke
this API
right right then mapping will only be
happen with this
method when first name is present if
first name is not present it this this
will not be
invoked right for the last name I have
mentioned required equals to false so
even if user do not pass the last name
right it would be considered as
null okay so now let's see that with the
one uh sample uh so
here request mapping I have keep value
equals to first
name let's create one more at theate
request
param or name equals to because I told
you either you can choose value or you
can choose name uh
last name
and I have mentioned it
that required equals to false it is not
required string last name so it user can
send it in the API or cannot send it so
let's say output is fetch user details
of the first name
plus and last
name I'll print this like what the last
name
comes okay and it will return it
so generally I have used at theate rest
controller at theate response body is
not
required okay so let's try to hit
it okay so I have started the server now
let's run
it Local
Host API
SL fetch user
first name equals
to I am passing
Shan and I am not passing last name
because that is not mandatory so I am
not passing so what it say that fetch
user details of Shan and last name is
null but what if
I miss the first name itself and I pass
last
name now now here if you see
that it's not able to resolve the API
itself why because I have tell that this
is mandatory by default request
parameter is true okay so the mapping
happens such that the URL fetch
user where first name should be present
it should be present then only this
method should get invoked okay so
request parameter is clear right so now
you need to understand that the
framework spring framework automatically
perform type conversion here from the
request parameter string representation
to a specific type so generally these
all type conversion it support primitive
types it support support
wrapper string enums and custom object
type so this part is clear right this is
very simple let's say you are passing at
theate API SL fetch
user question mark age equal to 28 right
or age equals to anything just what I'm
trying to say that's any number so this
is ultimately a string currently but in
the
API you right here API we are catching
it in
in right so there is some type cast time
casting happen right so that framework
automatically performs
so primitive type typ casting okay this
is an integer this string this value can
be typ casted to integer yes it will do
so those type casting it will perform
but let's say that uh you want to
specifically let's say uh
23/4
SL 1999 something some date this is a
string now you want to type cast into
particular date object this is my date
so how this string will get type casted
to date how you have to put certain
logic right that you can do it through
custom object type right I will explain
you this custom object type with very
simple example right this will help you
clarify you can write your own custom uh
object types
also so understand this with
this so very simple class right I have
created a controller class with rest
controller put a request mapping base
API
method one simple get method with this
path which is mapped to this
method right these are the three request
parameters now this is the first name
now my requirement is that whatever the
first name should come user can also
give like this
user can also give like this s r a y a n
SS some all small all big some big some
small because it's a string right there
is no guarantee how the data will come
but before you assign this value to
this method
parameter you want to do certain kind of
let's say some type casting or certain
you your logic custom logic that you can
help do through property editor so this
property editor or how we can use this
there is something annotation
called init
binder so in this controller class I
have written one innit binder right I
have put this
annotation so what this annotations
tells to the springboard that hey for
each method whenever any API get
involved
first run this
binder and see if any of its
parameter required certain
pre-processing so what I am doing is
here if you see that uh it accept one
parameter called binder it register we
can register our custom editor so I'm
writing our custom editor so this is I
have write a custom editor but what it
accept three parameters so first one is
what should be the return type
ultimately so it would be uh so what is
the String actually you wanted right so
I wanted a
string right so this string matches with
this a string do
class right so string do class yes it
matches this method parameter matches
this and also check the name request
param name first name okay exactly match
this then what is the
property editor you have to run so I
have written custom editor right so I
have written my own custom editor I have
written one class my first name property
editor you have to extend it property
editor support because this is the
parameter which it accept property
editor
support so I have created a first name
property editor child of this one so I
have Creed an object of it so what it
will do is it will invoke it set as text
because everything which comes from the
URI it is nothing but a
text now it comes as a text now you can
do anything now here if you see that I
have done the trimming and also make it
to the lower case so even though I'm
passing the capital letter ultimately it
will do the trim and make it a small
case right and then ultimately it will
get set into the first
name so you got it you can do custom
object types also with
this then there is something called path
variable so path variable is like used
to extract the value from the path of
the
URL and bind it to the controller method
parameter so here if you see that at
theate API
SL fetch user slash let's say I pass
this is 1 2 3 4 5 like in the the API
itself there's nothing like a question
mark and value equals to 1 2 3 4 5 no
those are request parameter this is path
parameter within the path itself API
path itself there is certain data you
have
provided right so you have to extract
the value and push it into the
method parameter okay so generally your
API is like API
SL fetch user SL CT in ID so generally
this cly bres right this is like a
dynamic some value can come inside this
1 2 3 4 5 8 7 something some string you
have to do the
mapping so this is where we are done so
there is a normal class uh simple class
which I marked as rest controller put
the base at the rest API now this is the
get call and I have done a mapping that
this is the path fetch user first
name first name
so like it can come anything right any
string but I have given any uh this is
the first name and now I have to fetch
this value to a method parameter so this
is the method it will map to because I
have return this get mapping on top of
it now this is the at theate path
variable is The annotation which tells
the spring board that that in this
path fetch out this first name which is
this part let's say if user is passing
this fetch out
this right so value of all this first
name and put it into
this like
this okay so now there is something
called request body so it bind the body
of the HTTP request typically Json or
XML to controller method parameter Java
object so here very very simple it's all
simple so here if you see that the
similar class I have created a
controller class right in this
method right this is the API let's say I
am creating a post mapping so let's say
this is the post request save user right
and in the method parameter it's an
object user object user object and I
have put it as request
body so now in the request body a Json
will come Json object will come now Json
object like this so I am passing in the
request so here the data raw here I'm
passing Json so it has username and
email so those will ultimately get
mapped to this user how spring boot
might use either I think G Jon or
Jackson out of this two libraries the
using this two
libraries this Json object is type cast
to this object from this Json object to
this Java object it
construct right so it request body I
have annotated with request body means
we are telling a spring board that hey
whatever the API coming check out its
body and whatever the data you see you
have to map it to this and in the user
class I have created this user
class and the user class I have created
two things username and email so now if
you notice that email I have kept
exactly same as this Json key so Jackson
or Json whatever Library they can easily
identify okay this name is exactly same
as this so This value should be mapped
to this but now here if you see that it
is is here user undor name and here it
is username so it will not get maap but
just to show you I have here tell that
we can also do that put Json property
this is Jackson I have used I have put
this annotation key that Json property
in the Json this field user name should
get mapped to
username right so and we have a getter
Setter get 10 Setter keys so Jackson
will invoke it to set the
values so got it so now when this method
get invoked so user do username you will
find out this Shan and user. email you
will find out this dummy
value
okay and we have last thing is response
entity so
now it represent the entire HTTP
response till now you know two things
controller and rest
controller controller you know that if
you don't provide at theate response
Body by default spring boot will try to
render it consider as a view
name right but the name rest controller
inherently has atate response body right
and then the name itself like rest
controller so what ultimately tells is
that all the response of this rest
controller is considered as an HTTP
response only right
so in this response entity what response
entity says that it represent the entire
HTTP response so in a response there are
multiple part we have body we have
status we have header so this response
body which rest controller has is
nothing but this specific part it talk
about this
part right response entity is like
combination of all this is known as
response entity so here in this one
sample this method is returning response
entity string so here what it whatever
it process let's say whatever value it
fetches from DB or
something I am creating a response
entity Dot
right first setting status I setting
status HTTP okay means 200 successfully
if it is a bad request or if it is a
validation failure select an appropriate
response
code right so currently this
successfully done so I'm selecting the
HTTP status code AS okay 200 and then
put a body my my actual response the
content I have put in the body
even if I want I can put header also
more
details so the complete with status body
header everything that is known as
response
entity so in rest
controller when we are just simply
returning a string not response
entity spring boot will always
considered as a rest controller that
this string would be considered as an
HTTP
response and and if it is an HTTP
response means it's considered as a
response entity only right so internally
spring boot create response entity only
like this
only response entity of a
string when we are simply returning a
string in case of rest
controller but in case of controller
that's not
true right that's not true internally
internally spring boot will not create
response entity because for
controller if response body is not
provided it will considered as a view
name so I can show you now let's say I'm
passing
controller I am not passing here
response
body right when I'm passing response
body annotate response body then
internally will create response entity
for this
string but when I am not creating
response
body and let's let me try to run it I
have started the
server let's hit the same API
again see some error why because this
output whatever the name fetch user
details of let's say sh this string it
is considered as a name of the view and
try to find out those file and wanted to
render it right so it internally didn't
create it as a response
entity okay so for this for today I will
keep it here and I will cover the rest
of the topic in the next part of it okay
team any doubt please feel free to ping
me in the comment section and we'll uh
see you soon thank you bye